Guide to the Joan G. Paull papers, 1972-1992 MS2038
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Joan G. Paull papers
1972-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Paull, Joan G.
MS2038
1 Linear Feet
Collection contains periodicals related to the Chesapeake and Ohio (C & O) Canal and the National Historical Parks. The material dates from 1972-92 with the bulk of the records covering the years 1983 to 1986.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
This collection of materials was originally donated by Joan Paull to the C&O Canal Association for inclusion in their archives. In 1996, the C&O Canal Association donated their archives to the Special Collections Department of the Gelman Library. Future accretions from Ms. Paull are anticipated, particularly relating to the Riley's Lockhouse program and the Potomac Valley Commission. Upon their donation, the Joan Paull Papers were found to include some material relating to her coordination of volunteer activities and work as a Level Walker for the C&O Canal Association. These materials have been placed with the C&O Canal Association Records.
Historical or Biographical Note
Joan G. Paull was born in Washington, D. C., and has been a life-long resident of the area. She is married to Norman Paull and has a daughter, Diane. A teacher by profession, she has always given much time and effort to community service. With the C&O Canal Association she was Chair of Work Parties for eleven years. This involved recruiting and supervising volunteers to do work projects assigned by the staff of the C&O Canal National Historical Park. One of her major projects was to repair a cabin at the Paw Paw campground and staff it with volunteer campground supervisors on summer weekends; the flood of 1985 damaged the cabin and brought the project to an end. She did important work in organizing volunteer work parties to repair damage from that flood. She was a Level Walker for the C&O Canal Association on Level 8 (Swain's Lock to Pennyfield Lock) for the same length of time. As a Level Walker she walked her Level every two or three months, recording events of nature, users of the canal and towpath, and problems to be called to the attention of the Association or the National Park Service. Active with the Girl Scouts for 31 years, she combined Scouting with the C&O Canal by creating and co-leading the program where Girl Scouts act as docents at Riley's Lockhouse on the canal. This program has introduced a whole generation of girls to regional history. Ms. Paull has also volunteered with the Smithsonian Folk Festival for 22 years.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains periodicals related to the Chesapeake and Ohio (C&O) Canal and the National Historical Parks. The material dates from 1972-92 with the bulk of the records covering the years 1983-86. Many local publications have articles in this collection such as "The Washington Post," "The Towline" (publication of the C&O Canal), "The Montgomery Journal," "The Montgomery County Sentinel," "The Gaithersburg Gazette," "The Frederick Post," and other local and national publications.
These papers were gathered by Joan Paull during her years of greatest involvement with the C&O Canal Association. Included in the collection are: photocopies of newspaper clippings and articles about the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park (C&O Canal NHP) which give a real flavor of what the C&O Canal NHP meant to the public and how it was used by them in the 1980's; publications by the National Park Service about the C&O Canal NHP, such as trail guides, facilities descriptions, and schedules for boat rides and concerts; and material about the region in which the C&O Canal NHP lies, such as tourist information for the Potomac Valley, the Cumberland Valley, and the Hagerstown-Washington County area.
Washington (D.C.); Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park; Chesapeake and Ohio Canal (Md. and Washington, D.C.); Chesapeake & Ohio Canal Association; Paull, Joan G.
- "Building a New Life" article by Sarah Booth Conroy including photos in The Washington Post, 1972 May 06 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historic Park (C&O Canal NHP) Hiking/Bicycling Information, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
- C&O Canal NHP visitor use Facilities, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
- National Park Service (NPS) agreement for individual voluntary services, 1975 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
- C&O Canal NHP visitor use facilities, 1975 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Towline, vol. 1 no. 1, July August, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Strolling Through History" article including photo in The Washington Post, Circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- C&O Canal NHP general plan, 1976 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- C&O Canal NHP calendar of events, 1976 March (Box 1, Folder 9)
- C&O Canal NHP calendar of events, 1973 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Towline vol. 2 no. 1, summer, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Towline vol. 2 no. 2, fall, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Unlock Magic of Canals" article by Heidi Hughes and Jerry Franklin including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1976 October 04 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- The Towline vol. 3 no. 1, winter, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- The Towline vol. 3 no. 2 spring/summer, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "A Delightful Day on the C&O Canal" article by Blanca Poteat including photo in The Sentine Montgomery County, 1977 May 05 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Tribute to Man Who Saved the C&O Canal" article by Paul Hodge including photo in The Washington Post, 1977 May 05 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "A Tribute to Douglas on the C&O Canal" article by Karen Dewitt including photos in The Washington Post, 1977 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "A Tranquil Barge Voyage to Another Era" article by Melinda Beck including photos in The Washington Post, 1977 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- The Towline vol. 3 no. 3, fall, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- The Towline vol. 4 no. 1, spring, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "On a barge on C&O: 'Canal Rats' Adrift down Memory Lane" article by Carol Kracoff including photo in The Washington Post, 1978 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- The Towline vol. 4 no. 2, fall, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "C&O Canal Barge in Drydock; Lower Canal Dramed for Repairs" clipping with photos in The Washington Post, 1978 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- The Towline vol. 4 no. 1, winter, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Faithful Hikers" clipping with photo in The Sentinel Montgomery County, 1979 May 03 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "After Seven Bridgeless Years..." article by Jeannette Belliveau including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1979 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "A Stroll Along the Canal" clipping with in The Montgomery Journal, 1979 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Memo from Glenn M. DeMarr, Construction Representatives, Land use Coordination,, to William R. Failor, superintendent, C&O Canal NHP, 1979 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- C&O Canal NHP development concept plan, Great Falls, Maryland, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- The Towline vol. 6 no. 1, winter, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- "Barging Down the River" article by Fred Gebhart including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1980 March 04 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- " 'Canal Clipper' Off and Running" clipping with photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1980 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- "Barging In..." clipping including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1980 May 07 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- C&O Canal, Cumberland/North Branch, Environmental Assessment, 1980 November (Box 1, Folder 35)
- C&O Canal NHP press release, Circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- "Douglas Honored Jan. 25" article in The Washington Post, 1981 January (Box 1, Folder 37)
- "State Wants to Save Farm as Crucial Link for Parks" article by Paul Hodge including photo in The Washington Post, 1981 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- "Canal Clipper is Off Again" article including photo in The Sentinel Montgomery County, 1981 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Hikanation Arrival, C&O Canal Segment news release, 1981 May 09-12 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Untitled clipping with photo of jogger on towpath in The Washington Post, 1981 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- C&O Canal NHP calendar of events, 1982 March (Box 1, Folder 42)
- The Towline vol. 7 no. 1, spring, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- "Annual C&O Canal Hike April 24" article in The Sentinel Montgomery County, 1982 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- "'River Man' Remembers Seneca Creek Back When" article by Morris Fredin including photos in The Washington Post, 1982 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- "Canal Trip Offers Engaging Lesson in History" article by Juan Jose Lulli including photo in The Gaithersburg Gazette, 1982 August 05 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- C&O Canal NHP bulletin "Caution" restoration projects, 1982 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Members C&O Canal NHP Advisory Commission mailing list, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- NPS Agreement for individual voluntary services form #10-85, 1983 January (Box 1, Folder 49)
- NPS Parental approval form #10-89, 1983 January (Box 1, Folder 50)
- "Clipping Along the C&O Canal" article by Jeffrey Finn including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1983 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- C&O Canal Williamsport development concept plan and assessment, 1983 May (Box 1, Folder 52)
- C&O Canal NHP visitor information, summer, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- C&O Canal NHP Piedmont District scheduled activities, 1983 July (Box 1, Folder 54)
- C&O Canal NHP Piedmont District scheduled activities, 1983 August (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Cumberland Valley Revue brochure, 1983 August (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Potomac Valley Revue brochure, 1983 August (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Your Day in Rock Creek Park Flier, 1983 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- "Farmer Honored for Work" article in The Montgomery Journal, 1983 November 01 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Untitled article about closure of water pumps on C&O Canal in The Montgomery County Sentinel, 1983 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- "George Wolfe, ex-mule driver, dies at age 89" obituary in The Washington Post, 1983 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- C&O Canal NHP brochure with map, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Pepco vs. the C&O Canal statement with charts and illustration by Edwin F. Wesley Jr., member of C&O Canal Advisory Commission, Circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- C&O Canal NHP food damage report, 1984 January 14-17 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- "C&O Towpath Hit Hard by Flooding" article by Joan McQueeney Mitric in The Montgomery Journal, 1984 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- C&O Canal NHP Commission meeting agenda, 1984 March 03 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- "Towpath Damage Put at $580,000" article in The Montgomery Journal, 1984 March 03 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- "See and Ah at the C&O" article in Shop Talk, 1984 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- "Canal Park Gifts Sought" article by Linda Duffield including photo in The Washington Post, 1984 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- "Tasks Around Town" clipping in The Washington Post, 1984 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- "Towpath Trekkers" article by Angus Phillips including photos in The Washington Post, 1984 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- "We Enjoy Glorious Canal Thanks to Bill Douglas" editorial including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1984 May 01 (Box 1, Folder 72)
- "Office Seeks Swimmer Barricades on Potomac" article by Dan Beyers including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1984 October 04 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Rock Creek Foliage Day flyer, 1984 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- "Md. Train station becoming Museum" article by Linda Duffield including photo in The Washington Post, 1984 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Concerts on the canal schedule, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Great Falls Park Brochure, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- "Memories" clipping with photo in The Montgomery Journal, Circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- "Spring Hike on C&O to honor Justice Douglas" article, Circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- "Life in a Lockhouse on the C&O Canal" article by Angus Phillips including photo in The Washington Post, 1985 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- C&O Canal NHP list of phone numbers, 1985 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- "C&O Washout Yields Anglers' Bonanza" article by Tom Kenworthy including photo in The Washington Post, 1985 August 12 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Size of the C&O Rupture Suprises Rangers, Slows Repair Work" article by Zita Arocha in The Washington Post, 1985 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "The C&O Canal" article by Eugene L. Meyer including photo by Stephen R. Brown in The National Geographic Traveler Vol. II No. 3, autumn, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Floodwaters Swamp Homes" article by Ben L. Herring including photos in The Montgomery Journal, 1985 November 08 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Flood Victims begin Task of Cleaning Up" article y Cynthia Durcanin including photos in The Montgomery Journal, 1985 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Towpath Report, 1985 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Canal Clipper schedule, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Towpath Report, 1986 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Canal repairs to Cause Closings" article by Clandia Levy including map and photos in The Washington Post, 1986 March 06 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Letter from Dick Stanton, Superintendent, C&O Canal NHP, to volunteers with attached sign-up form, 1986 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- C&O Canal Clean-up Camporee brochure, with memorandum form Richard L. Stanton to C&O Canal Association members, June-July, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Montgomery Asks ICC for Rail Land" article by Ann Mariano in The Washington Post, 1986 July 19 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Memories" clipping with photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1986 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "A ranger keeps the peace Along the C&O Canal" article by Eugene l. Meyer including photo in The Washington post, 1986 August 28 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "19th Annual Labor Day Event, Town of Kensington, Md." flier, 1986 September 01 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "Pact Near on Lease of C&O Parcel" article by Ann Mariano including photo in The Washington Post, 1986 September 06 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Old Technology but not yet Obsolete" article y Robert D. Hershey, Jr. including photo in The New York Times, 1986 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- C&O Canal NHP Commission meeting agenda, 1986 September 20 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "Proposed Hydro Plants Hit" article by Beth Kaiman including photo in The Washington Post, 1986 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Canal Camporee Nominated" article in NCR Partnerships, fall, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- "House to be Restored at site on C&O Canal" article by Ann Mariano in The Washington Post, 1986 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Canal Boats schedule, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Concerts on the Canal schedule, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- "Mobil Invites You to Free Concerts on the Canal" advertisement in The Washington Post, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- C&O Canal NHP alternative recreational facilities list, Circa 1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Potomac Valley Revue brochure, 1987 January (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Invitation to exhibit of works of art by John Louis Wellington, Cumberland, Md., 1987 May 16-24 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- "Rep. Byron seeks local help in Policing the C&O Canal" article by Eric Planin in The Washington Post, 1987 July 28 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- "C&O Canal Policing Bill Eyed in Md." Article by Claudia Levy in The Washington Post, 1987 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- "William O. Douglas's Historic Hike Saved the C&O Canal" article including photo in Naturalist News, 1987 September (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Chart of legal sizes and limits for fishing in the District of Columbia, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Concerts on the Canal schedule, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- "Mikulski Receives Request" article by Chuck Biedka in Cumberland Times-News, 1988 January 06 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- "On Potomac Dying Season Begins" article by Jaleh Hagigh including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1988 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- "Gore family is target of tree-cutting investigation" article by Daniel Isaac including map and photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1988 September 13 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- "Rewatering C&O is focus of study" article by Deb Riechmann in The Montgomery Journal, 1988 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Calendar listing for bird walk in The Montgomery Journal, 1988 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- "Group Trims Away Trees and Years from Canal Depot at White's Ferry" article by Thomas Pelton including photos in The Washington Post, 1989 January 09 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- "Tree-dom" editorial in The Montgomery Journal, 1989 January 22 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- "Riley's Lock" article in The Washington Post, 1989 March 31 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "One's Level Best on the Canal" article by Pamela Kessler including photo in The Washington Post, 1989 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- "The C&O Canal" article by Matthew Lewis including photos in The Washington Post, 1989 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- "Fascination with Canal Endures for a Lifetime" article by Claudia Levy including photo in The Washington Post, 1989 August 14 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Raymond M. Riley, four obituaries from The Frederic Post, The Washington Post, and two unidentified newspapers, 1989 September 12 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Conceptual study of bridge options over the C&O Canal, Cumberland, Md. With canal parkway profile and details, by Maryland's State Highway Administration, 1989 September (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Study and map of canal parkway and related development Cumberland, Md., 1989 November (Box 2, Folder 46)
- C&O Canal NHP brochure with map, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Glenn Echo Park brochure, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- "Federal Budget Crisis Leaves Park goers without Rangers" article by Mary-Ellen Phelps, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- "Preservationists Balk at Plan for C&O Parkway" article by Eugene L. Meyer including photos in The Washington Post, 1990 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Memo from Staff Curator, C&O Canal NHP, to Superintendent through Chief Ranger, Interpretive Specialist, 1990 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- "Got Cabin Fever? Butt Heads with Billy Goat Trail" article by Karen Kinser including map and photos in The Montgomery Journal, 1990 January 26 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- "Wake up South Cumberland" article in The Informer vol. 1 no. 4, 1990 January (Box 2, Folder 53)
- "Great Falls Park to Charge Association" article by Valerie Chow Bush in The Washington Post, 1990 July 29 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- "William Davies, Retired U.S. Geological Official, Dies" obituary in The Washington Post, 1990 July 29 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- "24,000 Volunteer to Serve Community" article in The Montgomery Journal, 1990 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- C&O Canal NHP boat trips schedule, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Concerts on the Canal schedule, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Great Falls Park brochure, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Great Falls Tavern brochure, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Cumberland Valley Revuew brochure, 1991 March (Box 2, Folder 61)
- C&O Canal NHP Facilities guide brochure, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- "A Historical Prime" clipping with photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1992 January 25 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- "Gap Bridged to Falls Overlook" article by George Bennett including photo in The Montgomery Journal, 1992 July 17 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- "Great Falls Rebridged" article including photo in The Washington Post, 1992 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 65)
- C&O Canal NHP schedule of events, 1992 September (Box 2, Folder 66)
- C&O Canal NHP schedule of events, 1992 October (Box 2, Folder 67)
- "Canal Restoration nearly complete-without the mules" article by Deb Riechmann, Circa 1993 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- The Abner Cloud House brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Announcing C&O Boat Trips for Friends of the Canal flyer, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
- C&O Canal boat replica brochure, Cumberland, Md, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
- C&O Canal NHP mileage chart from Georgetown to Seneca, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
- C&O Canal NHP natural resources inventory, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
- C&O Canal NHP system survey form, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
- C&O Canal NHP visitor information, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
- C&O Canal NHP visitory information, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
- C&O National Monument notification card for scouts, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Canal Clipper schedule, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
- "Chesapeake and Ohio Canal, 1828-1924" article, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
- Copy of page from unidentified source describing rocks, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
- Ferry Hill Place brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
- "Golden Days Gone for Oldest Mine in Maryland" article including photo in The Washington Post, undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
- Great Falls of the Potomac brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
- Hagerstown-C&O Canal-Williamsport bicycle loop route description, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
- Hagerstown Washington County Chamber of Commerce brochure with map, undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Harpers Ferry Center brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
- Hotels/Motels along the C&O Canal Towpath from Georgetown to Cumberland list, undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Jonathan Hager House and Hager Museum, Hagerstown, Md., brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
- More aobut the C&O Canal outings for the entire family program schedule, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
- National Parks in the Capital Area representatives dinner table directory, undated (Box 2, Folder 90)
- National Parks in the Capitol Area representatives dinner table directory, undated (Box 2, Folder 91)
- NPS Agreement for sponsored voluntary services form #10-86 with attachments, undated (Box 2, Folder 92)
- Old Angler's Inn safety brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 93)
- "The Old C&O Canal: A New Look Comes in a Spring Book" article by Jean Alexander including drawing in The Montgomery County Sentinel, undated (Box 2, Folder 94)
- "Park Service to Revitalize C&O Canal" article by Deb Riechmann including photo in The Montgomery Journal, undated (Box 2, Folder 95)
- Paw Paw Tunnel brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 96)
- "A Pipeline for Montgomery County?" article from Sierra Club publication, undated (Box 2, Folder 97)
- "A Potomac Sampler" article by Ron Canter including map and photo, undated (Box 2, Folder 98)
- "Rebuild the foot bridges at Great Falls article by William E. Hanna, Jr., undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
- Recipes using paw paws from The Wild Flower, undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
- Seneca Sandstone Biking Trail guide by Sugarloaf Regional Trails, undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
- "Spring Barges In on the C&O Canal" clipping with photos in The Montgomery County Sentinel, undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
- Swam's Boathouse business card, undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
- Violette's Lock safety brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 104)
- "Wednesday's 'David' Wasn't All That Destructive" article including photos in The Montgomery Journal, undated (Box 2, Folder 105)
- "Yesterday Lives Again" brochure by Washington County [Maryland] Historical Society, undated (Box 2, Folder 106)